Register of the Malbone W. Graham papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Malbone W. Graham papers
1912-1956
67003
Hoover Institution Archives
12 manuscript boxes, 2 card file boxes, 1 oversize folder (6.0 linear feet)
The Malbone Graham papers largely consist of diplomatic correspondence, reports, and summaries of conversations that Graham had with leading personalities in Eastern Europe and academic specialists in the West. The materials reflect Graham’s interest in the political order that emerged in post-World War I Europe and especially that which developed in Eastern Europe. Graham studied the successful efforts of Finland, Poland, Lithuania, Latvia, and Estonia to secure their independence in the wake of the collapse of the Russian empire. His research also included the failed attempt of the Ukrainian independence movement to achieve statehood.
Graham, Malbone W. (Malbone Watson), 1898-1965.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1967.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1898 March 26 Born, Bogota, Colombia
1918 Awarded bachelor's degree, University of California at Berkeley
1921 Awarded doctorate, University of California at Berkeley
1923 Author, The Controversy between the United States and the Allied Governments Respecting Neutral Rights and Commerce during the Period of American Neutrality, 1914-1917
1924 Joined faculty of University of California at Los Angeles (UCLA)
1934 Promoted to full professorship at UCLA
1936-1941 Author, Diplomatic Recognition of the Border States: I. Finland, II. Estonia, III. Latvia
1948 Author, American Diplomacy in the International Community
1965 October 16 Died, Santa Monica, California
Scope and Content of Collection
The Malbone Graham papers reflect Graham’s interest in the political order that emerged in post-World War I Europe, and especially that which developed in Eastern Europe. Graham studied the successful efforts of Finland, Poland, Lithuania, Latvia, and Estonia to secure their independence in the wake of the collapse of the Russian empire. His research also included the failed attempt of the Ukrainian independence movement to achieve statehood.
The papers largely consist of diplomatic correspondence, reports, and summaries of conversations that Graham had with leading personalities in Eastern Europe and academic specialists in the West. These summaries describe some of the obstacles on the road to independence for the Baltic States, Poland, and Finland. The diplomatic correspondence includes letters from various governments recognizing the independence of these new states.
The papers also contain several of Graham’s writings on Estonia, Finland, Czechoslovakia, and Ukraine. The card files in the collection provide an extensive bibliography of works on Lithuania, Estonia, and Finland. Additionally, there are some materials in the papers relating to the League of Nations, China, and the Soviet Union, as well as a small amount of documents relating to Yugoslavia, Greece, and a number of other European countries.
League of Nations.; Baltic States--History.; Europe, Eastern--History.; Finland--History.
- Correspondence, 1936, 1953-1954 (Box 1)
  - Harper, Samuel N., 1936 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Raila, Bronys, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 1: 2)
- Speeches and Writings, 1932-1937 (Box 1)
  - Text on Estonian struggle for independence, 1932 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - "The Diplomatic Recognition of the Border States. Part 1: Finland,", 1934 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - "Fifteen Years of Czechoslovak Foreign Policy,", 1934 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - "The Present Status of the Ukrainian Question,", 1937 April 15 (Box-folder 1: 6)
- Notes and Diaries, 1916-1938 (Boxes 1-2)
  - Notes on Poland, 1916-1926 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Notes on Russia, 1925 (Box-folder 1: 8-9)
  - Original notes and data on Latvia, Lithuania, 1926 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Notes on Estonia and Finland, and general Baltic notes, 1927 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Miscellaneous memoranda of conversations, 1930 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Notes, diary, and conversations in Europe, 1930 July-October (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - European notes and diary, 1930 July-November (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Notes on Estonia, 1932 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Diary, notes, and memoranda of conversations, 1938 (Box-folder 2: 7)
- Subject File, 1912-1953 (Boxes 3-11)
  - General, 1919, 1930
    - Memorandum, 1930 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - "Le problème de l'Europe orientale,", 1919 (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - Summaries of conversations with Hans Kelen, Lawrence Martin, and David Hunter Miller, 1930 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Armenia, 1919-1920
    - Accord, correspondence, and memoranda, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    - Brochure containing position paper, 1919 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Baltic States, 1917-1952
    - General, 1919-1933
      - Commission des Affaires Baltiques, procès-verbaux nos. 1-18, 1919 (Box-folder 3: 6)
      - Memorandum, 1933 (Box-folder 3: 7)
      - Reports on Baltic conferences, 1920-1923 (Box-folder 3: 8)
      - Speech by Oskar Kallas, 1923 (Box-folder 3: 9)
    - Estonia, 1917-1932
      - Correspondence and diplomatic note, 1920-1932 (Box-folder 3: 10)
      - Decree, declarations, and speech, 1917-1919 (Box-folder 3: 11)
      - Diplomatic correspondence, 1919 (Box-folder 3: 12-13)
      - Letters of recognition of Estonian independence, 1918-1926 (Box-folder 3: 14)
      - Memoranda, 1924-1936 (Box-folder 3: 15)
      - Press comments, 1921 (Box-folder 3: 16)
      - Writings, 1917-1932
        - "Events in Estonia, Sept. 1919," (Box-folder 3: 17)
        - "Original Notes and Documents on Estonia,", 1917-1932 (Box-folder 3: 18)
        - Piip, Antonius, "Estonia in Eastern Europe,", 1925 (Box-folder 3: 19)
    - Latvia, 1917-1941
      - Bulletins, chronology, diplomatic correspondence, and memoranda of conversations, 1917-1930 (Box-folder 3: 20)
      - Clipping, 1920 (Box-folder 4: 1)
      - Diplomatic correspondence and reports, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 4: 2)
      - Latvian Information Bulletin, 1941 (Box-folder 4: 3)
      - Letters of recognition of Latvian independence, 1919-1922 (Box-folder 4: 4)
      - Memoranda, 1937 (Box-folder 4: 5)
      - Memorandum and reports, 1937 (Box-folder 4: 6)
      - Pamphlet, 1920 (Box-folder 4: 7)
      - Statement, letter, and summaries of conversations with Alfred Bilmanis and Olgerds Groswalds, 1938-1941 (Box-folder 4: 8)
      - Writings, 1932-1938
        - Piip, Antonius, "The Liberation of Latvia,", 1932 (Box-folder 4: 9)
        - Slaucitajs, Leonids, "Notes on the General Geography of Latvia,", 1933 (Box-folder 4: 10)
        - "La Lettonie avant et après l'établissement du régime autoritaire,", 1935 (Box-folder 4: 11)
        - Articles on culture, 1937 (Box-folder 4: 12)
        - Article on Kārlis Ulmanis, 1938 (Box-folder 4: 13)
    - Lithuania, 1916-1952
      - Excerpt from monograph on Lithuanian independence movement, 1940 (Box-folder 4: 14)
      - Joseph J. Hertmanowicz papers, 1916-1935 (Box-folder 4: 15-16)
      - Julius J. Bielskis papers, 1919 (Box-folder 5: 1)
      - Letters of recognition of Lithuanian independence, 1918-1923 (Box-folder 5: 2)
      - Memorandum, 1933 (Box-folder 5: 3)
      - Report on Memel, 1932 (Box-folder 5: 4)
      - Reports, resolutions, and statements, 1916-1925
        - American Relief Fund for Lithuanian War Sufferers, 1916 (Box-folder 5: 5)
        - Lithuanian National Council, 1919-1925 (Box-folder 5: 6-7)
        - Lithuanian National Council, 1919-1925 (Box-folder 6: 1-2)
      - Speeches, 1917, 1952
        - By Malbone Graham, 1952 (Box-folder 6: 3)
        - By A. Smetona, "Die Litanische Frage,", 1917 (Box-folder 6: 4)
      - Memoranda, diplomatic correspondence, and notes, 1916-1935 (Box-folder 6: 5-7)
      - Memorandum and reports, 1936 (Box-folder 6: 8)
      - Summaries of conversations with Kazimieras Almanauskis, Julius J. Bielskis, Kazys Bizauskas, Josef L. Kunz, Boleslavas Pranas Mastaukas, and Vladimiras Soloveicikas, 1930-1952 (Box-folder 6: 9)
  - Caucasus and Trans-Caucasus, 1919-1920
    - Diplomatic correspondence, 1920 (Box-folder 6: 10)
    - Letters of recognition of Georgian independence, 1919 (Box-folder 6: 11)
    - Notes, report, speech, and statement, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 6: 12)
  - China, 1934-1942
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1934-1935 (Box-folder 6: 13)
    - Hanwell, Norman D., "Communism in Szechuan,", 1933-1934 (Box-folder 6: 14)
    - Compilation of articles selected by Norman D. Hanwell, 1934-1935 (Box-folder 6: 15-16)
    - Compilation of articles selected by Norman D. Hanwell, 1934 -1935 (Box-folder 7: 1-2)
    - Chapter of monograph on Japan and China, 1942 (Box-folder 7: 3)
  - Czechoslovakia, 1919-1935
    - Articles, 1920 (Box-folder 7: 4)
    - Letters of recognition of Czechoslovakian independence and other diplomatic correspondence, 1919-1922 (Box-folder 7: 5)
    - Summaries of conversations with Edward Beneš, Ales Brox, Jaroslav Kraus, and Stephen Osusky, 1930-1935 (Box-folder 7: 6)
  - Finland, 1918-1942
    - Articles, memoranda, and reports, 1918-1940
      - Foreign policy, 1918-1939 (Box-folder 7: 7-11)
      - German plans, 1920 (Box-folder 7: 12)
      - Ingria, 1931 (Box-folder 8: 1)
      - Karelia, 1931 (Box-folder 8: 2)
      - Presidential elections and politics, 1920-1931 (Box-folder 8: 3)
      - Recognition of independence, 1920-1935 (Box-folder 8: 4)
      - Russo-Finnish War, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 8: 5-8)
      - Social conditions, 1940 (Box-folder 8: 9)
    - Report on Estonia, 1919 (Box-folder 8: 10)
    - Summaries of conversations with Rudolf Holsti, Bertel Gronblom, Hjalmar Procopé, and Per Zilliacus, 1932-1942 (Box-folder 8: 11)
    - U.S. State Department documents and memorandum, 1919-1930 (Box-folder 8: 12)
    - Writing, commentary, and correspondence relating to Rudolf Holsti, 1919-1935 (Box-folder 8: 13)
    - Writings, 1930-1940
      - "Memoirs and Recollections of Rudolf Holsti: Abridgment of the Author's Memoirs,", 1930 (Box-folder 8: 14)
      - Bellquist, Eric Cyril, "Finnish Presidential Elections,", 1931 (Box-folder 8: 15)
      - Viljanen, Lauri, "Modern Finnish Literature,", 1938 (Box-folder 8: 16)
      - "Finland: The Question of Independence,", 1940 (Box-folder 8: 17)
  - Galicia, position paper, "The Political Status of Eastern Galicia,", 1922 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - Greece, summaries of conversations with Adamantios T. Polyzoides and Demetrios Sicilianos, 1935 (Box-folder 9: 2)
  - Hungary, introduction to lecture by Michael Karolyi, 1930 (Box-folder 9: 3)
  - Japan, summary of conversation with Inazo Nitobe, 1932 (Box-folder 9: 4)
  - League of Nations, 1919-1933
    - Committee on the Revision of the Covenant, 1930-1933
      - Memorandum by J. T. Shotwell, 1933 (Box-folder 9: 5)
      - Minutes of meeting, 1930 (Box-folder 9: 6)
      - Proposals, 1930 (Box-folder 9: 7)
    - Notes on Covenant taken by David Hunter Miller, 1919 (Box-folder 9: 8)
    - Speeches, 1919
      - Hoover, Herbert, 1919 (Box-folder 9: 9)
      - Villard, Oswald Garrison, 1919 (Box-folder 9: 10)
    - Summary of conversation with Gerald Abrahamson, 1930 (Box-folder 9: 11)
  - Netherlands, summary of conversation with H. A. Van Cleffens, 1930 (Box-folder 9: 12)
  - Poland, 1919-1935
    - Article and speech, 1923, 1935
      - Gidynski, Jospeh Cesirme, "Constitutional Development of Poland,", 1935 (Box-folder 9: 13)
      - Nowacki, Z., "Opportunity for America in Poland,", 1923 (Box-folder 9: 14)
    - Constitution and laws, 1935
      - Constitution, 1935 (Box-folder 9: 15)
      - Electoral by-laws, 1935 (Box-folder 9: 16-17)
      - Law governing presidential elections, 1935 (Box-folder 9: 18)
    - Election results, 1930 (Box-folder 9: 19)
    - Letters of recognition of Polish independence, 1919-1923 (Box-folder 9: 20)
    - Memorandum, 1930 (Box-folder 9: 21)
    - Reports, 1930, 1935
      - International Agricultural Conference, 1930 (Box-folder 9: 22)
      - Parliament, 1935 (Box-folder 9: 23)
  - Romania, summaries of conversations with George Boncesco and Juliu Maniu, 1930-1940 (Box-folder 9: 24)
  - Ruthenia, 1919, 1936
    - Article, 1919 (Box-folder 9: 25)
    - Summary of conversation with Alexander Sushko, 1936 (Box-folder 9: 26)
  - Soviet Union, 1930-1940
    - Bibliography, 1939 (Box-folder 10: 1)
    - Statement by Maxim Litvinov, 1930 (Box-folder 10: 2)
    - Summaries of conversations with Edward Everett Brodie, Constantine A. Oumansky, and Boris Skvirsky, 1930-1940 (Box-folder 10: 3)
    - Treaties of non-aggression and conciliation, 1932
      - With Finland, 1932 (Box-folder 10: 4-5)
      - With Poland, 1932 (Box-folder 10: 6)
    - Writings, 1930, 1939
      - Diary of a trip to the Soviet Union, 1930 (Box-folder 10: 7)
      - "A Sixth Visit to the Soviet Union,", 1939 (Box-folder 10: 8)
  - Ukraine, 1912-1936
    - Independence, 1914-1919
      - Articles, correspondence, and reports, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 10: 9-10)
      - Memorandum, 1914 (Box-folder 10: 11)
      - Petition, reports, and resolutions, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 10: 12)
    - Memorials and petition, 1918 (Box-folder 10: 13)
    - Reports and communiqués, 1918-1919
      - East Galicia, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 10: 14)
      - Relations with Poland, 1919 (Box-folder 10: 15)
      - Relations with Russia, 1918 (Box-folder 10: 16)
      - Ukrainian language, 1918 (Box-folder 10: 17)
    - Speech by Richard Kimens, 1918 (Box-folder 10: 18)
    - Summaries of conversations with Ralph L. Lutz, John Orlyk, Ivan Petrushevich, and Evan P. Sevidge, 1934-1936 (Box-folder 10: 19)
    - Writings and lectures, 1912-1935
      - Fédortchouk, Yaroslav, "Le réveil national des Ukrainiens,", 1912 (Box-folder 10: 20)
      - Fédortchouk, Yaroslav, "Memorandum on the Ukrainian Question in Its National Aspect,", 1914 (Box-folder 11: 1)
      - "Proclamation de l'indépendance de l'Ukraine,", 1919 (Box-folder 11: 2)
      - "A tous les peuples et à leurs gouvernements,", 1919 (Box-folder 11: 3)
      - "Aux nations civilisées,", 1919 (Box-folder 11: 4)
      - "The Case of the New Republics of Estonia, Latvia, Lithuania, and Ukraine,", 1919 (Box-folder 11: 5)
      - "The Cause of the Ukraine,", 1919 (Box-folder 11: 6)
      - "Déclaration du gouvernement de la république démocratique Ukrainenne,", 1919 (Box-folder 11: 7)
      - "La France et l'Ukraine,", 1919 (Box-folder 11: 8)
      - "The French Sabotage of the Peace Negotiations of the Western Ukrainian Republic in Paris, 1918-1919," (Box-folder 11: 9)
      - "Lux in Tenebris,", 1919 (Box-folder 11: 10)
      - "A New Project for the Destruction of Russ or How Polish Tyrants Contemplate the Extermination of the Ukrainian Race,", 1919 (Box-folder 11: 11)
      - "Notes historiques sur l'Ukraine,", 1919 (Box-folder 11: 12)
      - "Notes présentées par la délégation de la République Ukrainienne,", 1919 (Box-folder 11: 13)
      - "Le problème de l'Europe centrale,", 1919 (Box-folder 11: 14)
      - Choulguine, Alexandre, "Les problèmes de l'Ukraine,", 1919 (Box-folder 11: 15)
      - "Russian Land and Polish Men,", 1919 (Box-folder 11: 16)
      - "L'Ukraine de l'ancienne Autriche-Hongrie,", 1919 (Box-folder 11: 17)
      - Shelukhin, S., "Ukraine, Poland and Russia and the Right of the Free Disposition of the People,", 1919 (Box-folder 11: 18)
      - "Aux académies des sciences, universités et autres sociétés scientifiques du monde entier,", 1920 (Box-folder 11: 19)
      - "Rendons justice à l'Ukraine,", 1920 (Box-folder 11: 20)
      - Savidge, Ethan, "Some Aspects of the Ukrainian Problem as Seen in Historical Perspective,", 1935 (Box-folder 11: 21)
  - Versailles Peace Conference, Villard, Oscar Garrison, "The Working of the Peace Conference,", 1919 (Box-folder 11: 22)
  - Yugoslavia, Ristic, Dragisha N., "Foreign Relations of Yugoslavia, 1914-1934,", 1953 (Box-folder 11: 23)
- Printed Matter, 1915-1956 (Box 12)
  - Monographs, 1936-1950
    - Mason, John Brown, Hitler's First Foes: A Study in Religion and Politics, 1936 (Box-folder 12: 1)
    - Piip, Antoninus, Estlands Weg zur neuen Verfassung, 1936 (Box-folder 12: 2)
    - Italy and the County of Nice, 1940 (Box-folder 12: 3)
    - Pusta, Kaarel Robert, The Soviet Union and the Baltic States, 1943 (Box-folder 12: 4)
    - Nazi-Soviet Conspiracy and the Baltic States, 1948 (Box-folder 12: 5)
    - Human Rights and Genocide in the Baltic States, 1950 (Box-folder 12: 6)
  - Pamphlets, 1916-1946
    - Mémoire supplémentaire sur la question Yougoslave, 1916 (Box-folder 12: 7)
    - Overzicht van de voornaamste tot November 1939 in verband met den oorlogstoestand... (Box-folder 12: 8)
    - Holsti, Rudolf, Nicolas Politis, 1872-1942 (Box-folder 12: 9)
    - Bilmanis, Alfred, Relations between Latvia and Soviet-Russia in the Light of International Law, 1946 (Box-folder 12: 10)
  - Serial issues, 1915-1956
    - The Baltic Review, 1953 (Box-folder 12: 11)
    - Bulletin Yougoslave, 1915-1917 (Box-folder 12: 12)
    - Kristaus Karaliaus Laivas, 1956 (Box-folder 12: 13)
    - Meie Teg, 1941 (Box-folder 12: 14)
    - Revue Baltique, 1940 (Box-folder 12: 15)
- Card Files, 1920-1942 (Boxes 13-14)
  - Notes and bibliographic information relating to Lithuania, 1920-1942 (Box 13)
  - Bibliographic information relating to Estonia, 1920-1940 (Box 14)
  - Bibliographic information relating to Finland, 1920-1940 (Box 14)
- Oversize Materials, 1942-1945 (Map case)
  Scope and Contents note
  Eight American World War II propaganda posters.